Hello class, this is
another review question,
and we have a 39-year
-old female presenting
to her primary care
physician with a
depressed mood and an
inability to concentrate.
She reported reduced appetite
and trouble sleeping.
She is started on nortripilene.
The mechanism of action
of this drug is best
described as, well,
looking at this drug,
medication, we should
know that it comes under
the category of tricyclic
antidepressants.
So thinking about that
medication, we know
that it's not first
line for depression.
As a matter of fact,
if we had to say what
would have been the
best therapy for this
patient, it would have
been an SSRI, and those
are selective serotonin
reuptake inhibitors.
And the reason being is
that SSRIs don't have
the autonomic adverse
effects that the tricyclics
display. And remember,
with the tricyclics,
you're also having
blockade of the H1
receptor, and that can
lead to weight gain and
sedation, which may be
helpful in certain cases.
We know something like
doxapin can sometimes
be used for making
people able to sleep.
The other thing is that
tricyclics do block the
alpha receptor. So that
would mean that you would
get somewhat of a
relaxation of smooth muscle.
And if the patient was
taking the medication
and got up very quickly,
they could get orthostasis.
That's another autonomic
effect. And the
last big thing about
the tricyclics is that
they are blockers of the
muscarinic receptors.
So patients can,
to some degree, get
dryness, urinary
retention, constipation.
In the case of the heart,
there may be some blockade
of the M2 receptors,
and that can lead to a
situation where the patient
can experience tachycardia.
And going into this block
and talking about the
heart, we know that an
overdose of tricyclics can
cause convulsions,
cardiotoxicity, and coma. And the
reason being is that
tricyclics, they somewhat
display an effect that is
mimicking sodium channel
blockers. In an overdose,
you would get an increase
in QRS and even QT
interval. And the way we
manage that effect is by
giving sodium bicarbonate to
stabilize the sodium
channels. But looking at the
mechanisms, we did a good
review of tricyclics.
We want to know what the
antidepressant mechanism is.
Blockade of the dopamine
receptors, that's going
to pretty much apply to
the typical antipsychotics.
Like caliperidol, flufenazine,
perhaps chlorpromazine. and
those would be a problem
if you were worried about
somebody with Parkinson's
disease because if you
block D2 receptors in the
nigrostriadium, you're
going to get some degree of
rigidity, bradykinesia and
that is probably one of
the limiting effects of
the typical antipsychotics.
Blocking norepinephrine
and serotonin
reuptake, that is
probably the best
answer. that is what
tricyclics will do.
So B would be correct.
Blocking serotonin receptors,
that might be something
like trazodone.
Trazodone does have some
reuptake inhibition potential,
but it also can block
serotonin receptors. That's
why we call it a S-A-R-I or
a SARI. And remember, with
trazodone, while we're on
that topic, understand that
patients can experience this
idea of priapism, and that
can be due to the fact
that trazodone exhibits a
blockade of the alpha receptor,
and that causes excessive
smooth muscle relaxation
and increase in blood flow.
Blocking the mu
receptors, that could be
the antidote of
something like opioids
because opioids will
agonize the mu receptor
and they cause, of
course, pain relief.
But in worst case scenario,
when patients overdose,
we're really concerned with
respiratory depression.
and the way that would be
managed is by giving something
that blocks the mu receptors
like per se naloxone
and then blocking norepinephrine
and dopamine reuptake
that would be more of the
mechanism of bupropion
so if the patient was given
an ssri especially for
thinking about certain
populations that may have adverse
sexual effects, the way
we can manage is either
by lowering the dose of
the SSRI, perhaps giving a
drug for ED, or we could
change the drug altogether.
And we would want something
that doesn't have a reuptake
inhibition of serotonin,
and that would be bupropion.
And E would be the case
if I had put bupropion.
And remember, with
blupropion, we do also have to
consider the fact that it
does block the nicotinic
receptors. So, blupropion is
the one that we can sometimes
give in patients that are
trying to quit smoking.
So, again, this is just
showing the overall mechanism
of TCAs from the standpoint
of treating depression,
reuptake inhibition of
serotonin and norepinephrine,
but what limits their
use is again the
autonomic adverse effects
that I described, and
that's due to the blockade
of alpha-1 receptors,
histamine-1 receptors,
and muscarinic receptors.
Thank you for your
attention. Please let me know
if there's anything that
you want to review for
this topic or any other
topic. Have a great day.